<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/doc/en/tomcat_guide.xml" lang="en">
  <title>Tomcat Guide</title>

  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="nichoj@gentoo.org">Joshua Nichols</mail>
  </author>
  <abstract>
    This guide provides information on the layout, usage, and other things related to
    Tomcat version 5.5.x and later on Gentoo Linux.
  </abstract>

  <!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
  <!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
  <license/>

  <version>1.1</version>
  <date>2006-07-02</date>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
          Tomcat on Gentoo Linux is implemented a bit differently. This document should
          provide some basic information on how Tomcat is different with regard to
          Gentoo Linux. This document is based on Tomcat versions 5.5.x and later. Older
          versions of Tomcat should not be used, unless an application requires it.
        </p>
        <p>
          The biggest initial difference on Gentoo is Tomcat being spread out among
          multiple directories. That is due to most all applications on Gentoo adhering to
          FHS along with other Gentoo file location standards.
        </p>
        <p>
          One the other major differences is that Tomcat is compiled from source on
          Gentoo. Along with the latest versions of any dependencies and bundled libraries.
          Which will also be compiled from source. Due to some of Tomcat's bundled
          libraries and compile time dependencies. The amount of Java applications that
          will need to be compiled from source is considerable.
        </p>
        <p>
          These are not the only differences, but are the two main differences. The rest of
          this document will go into more detail about those and other differences.
        </p>
        <p>
          This document will not cover <uri link="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/">
          Java Servlet Specifications</uri>, nor general
          <uri link="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Tomcat configuration</uri>.
          This document assume the reader has a basic understanding of what a Java
          Web Application is, consists of, and basics of how to configure a container for the
          web application. Among the other things that are covered under the
       <uri link="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/">Java Servlet Specification</uri>.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Layout</title>
    <section>
      <title>Standard Tomcat Layout</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          The root directory of a typical Tomcat binary distribution is laid out as illustrated
          in the following listing.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Standard Tomcat Root Directory Layout">
/opt/tomcat-*/bin
/opt/tomcat-*/common
/opt/tomcat-*/conf
/opt/tomcat-*/logs
/opt/tomcat-*/server
/opt/tomcat-*/shared
/opt/tomcat-*/temp
/opt/tomcat-*/webapps
/opt/tomcat-*/work
        </pre>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Gentoo Tomcat Layout</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          To fit in with FHS and Gentoo standards, Tomcat has been dissected and installed
          into the following locations.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Gentoo Tomcat Layout">
/etc/tomcat-*/conf
/var/run/tomcat-*/work
/var/tmp/tomcat-*/temp
/var/lib/tomcat-*/webapps
/var/log/tomcat-*/logs
/usr/share/tomcat-*/bin
/usr/share/tomcat-*/common
/usr/share/tomcat-*/server
/usr/share/tomcat-*/shared
        </pre>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuration Files</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          In addition to simply moving the Tomcat <path>/conf</path> directory under
         <path>/etc</path>. Their is a Gentoo specific Tomcat configuration file
         <path>etc/conf.d/tomcat-*</path>. Which contains Tomcat variables that are
         sourced during start or stop. These variables are as follows:
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>
        	    JAVA_HOME this is set to <c>$(java-config --jdk-home)</c>, however this
                variable exists to allow Tomcat to run with a VM other than the system vm
              </li>
              <li>
        	    CATALINA_HOME this is typically set to <path>/usr/share/tomcat-*</path>
              </li>
              <li>
        	    CATALINA_BASE this is typically set to <path>/var/lib/tomcat-*</path>
              </li>
              <li>
        	    CATALINA_USER this is typically set to tomcat
              </li>
              <li>
        	    CATALINA_LIBDIR this is typically set to
                <path>/usr/share/tomcat-*/server/lib</path>
              </li>
              <li>
        	    CLASSPATH this is typically set to <c>${CATALINA_LIBDIR}</c>
              </li>
              <li>
        	    CATALINA_TMPDIR this is typically set to <path>/var/tmp/tomcat-*</path>
              </li>
              <li>
        	    TOMCAT_START this is typically set to "start", alternatives being "debug", 
                "start -security", "debug -security", or "jpda start"
              </li>
              <li>
        	    TOMCAT_STOP this is typically set to "stop"
              </li>
              <li>
        	    CATALINA_OPTS this is not set, but can be to pass options to Java or Tomcat
              </li>
            </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <p>
          Also installed into <path>/etc</path> is the Gentoo specific 
          <path>/etc/init.d/tomcat-*</path> init script. Tomcat on Gentoo no longer uses
          nor does it modify catalina.sh at all.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Web Applications</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          The directory /var/lib/tomcat-*/ contains a group of links as well as the webapps
          directory which houses the actual J2EE web applications. This directory serves as
          the hub and is referenced by Tomcat as the TOMCAT_BASE.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Gentoo Tomcat Base and webapp location">
conf -> /etc/tomcat5/default
logs -> /var/log/tomcat5/default
temp -> /var/tmp/tomcat5/default
webapps
work -> /var/run/tomcat5/default
        </pre>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Run Time Files</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          These directories hold logs, temp, and working files used by tomcat.
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>
        	    <path>/var/tmp/tomcat-*</path> Tomcat's temporary directory
              </li>
              <li>
        	    <path>/var/run/tomcat-*</path> Tomcat's working directory, where  JSPs
                .java sources and resulting binaries are compiled and stored
              </li>
              <li>
        	    <path>/var/log/tomcat-*</path> Tomcat's logging directory
              </li>
            </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Installation</title>
    <section>
      <title>Tomcat's Use Flags</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          Tomcat's use flags are not any different from use flags for any package on
          Gentoo. Most are self explanatory like doc, sources, and test. Documents, 
          sources, and since it's Java, JUnit tests. The other two are a little different.
        </p>
<!--
        <p>
          The puretls use flag effects the only optional compile time package at this time.
          When used, Tomcat will be compiled using
          <uri link="http://www.rtfm.com/puretls/">Claymore Systems's PureTLS</uri>
          instead of the default of using
          <uri link="http://java.sun.com/products/jsse/">Sun's JSSE</uri>.  This effects
          which SSL library the resulting Tomcat binaries will be built against. The puretls
          use flag is not widely used. At this time there are no official Tomcat binary
          releases built against PureTLS. If you decide to enable the puretls use flag.
          Please do not go complaining to the Tomcat community, unless it's related to
          filing a bug, development, or improvement with regard to PureTLS. Please do not
          expect much support from the Gentoo Java community on PureTLS with Tomcat
          either. The Gentoo Java team is limited to upstream as well.
        </p>
-->
        <p>
          The examples use flag should be used for anyone new to Tomcat,
          Java Web Application development, or just about anything beyond deploying
          existing applications. When set, the examples use flag will tell the ebuild to
          install the examples web application. Which contains the default, Tomcat is
          running page along with Tomcat's web based documentation. Without the
          examples useflag set, any request to <uri>http://127.0.0.1:8080</uri> will
          result with a blank page. Which is desired if Tomcat is a dependency for other
          wanted Java applications, where the examples will not be used. Most all can
          safely ignore this use flag, unless you are starting out.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Emerge  Tomcat</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          Once you have the desired use flags set in <path>/etc/make.conf</path> it's
          time to compile and install Tomcat. Tomcat as most all other Gentoo applications
          installs by doing
        </p>
        <pre caption="Command to download, compile, and install Tomcat">
emerge tomcat
        </pre>
        <warn>
          Due to compiling Tomcat from source, as well as all of Tomcat's depenencies,
          along with any and all bundled libraries, frameworks, and etc. The amount of
          dependencies, packages that need to be compiled before Tomcat, is
          considerable. Good news is, since it's Java, aside from download time, should
          compile rather quickly even on older machines.
        </warn>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Usage</title>
    <section>
      <title>Configuring Tomcat</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          Depending on what Tomcat will be used for one may or may not need to
          configure Tomcat. If Tomcat is a dependency of another application, which is
          installed in Tomcat's default webapps directory
          <path>/var/lib/tomcat-*/webapps</path>. One might be able to simple start
          Tomcat, and request the application via a browser or etc at
          http://127.0.0.1:8080/.
        </p>
        <p>
          For most others, developers, running more than one site under Tomcat, or etc.
          will need to edit Tomcat's main configuration file
          <path>/etc/tomcat-*/server.xml</path>. The syntax of that file, and
          configuration of Tomcat is beyond the scope of this document. Please refer to
          <uri link="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Tomcat documentation</uri>
          for more information.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using a custom VM</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          By default Tomcat will use the system VM controlled by <c>java-config</c> as
          per the JAVA_HOME variable in <path>/etc/conf.d/tomcat-*</path>. One can
          change that variable to any VM that is capable of running Tomcat. Then when
          Tomcat is started it will use the specified VM.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Starting/Stopping Tomcat</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          Tomcat is started and stopped the same as any service on Gentoo.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Start Stop Restart Tomcat">
/etc/init.d/tomcat-* start/stop/restart
        </pre>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tomcat's Standard Web Applications</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          By default we do not install Tomcat's examples web application. We do by default
          install Tomcat's admin and manager applications. However per upstream
          Tomcat policy, as username and password has to be configued. Prior to any
          web access one will have to manually edit
          <path>/etc/tomcat-*/tomcat-users.xml</path>
        </p>
        <pre caption="Admin and Manager Web Application URLs">
<uri>http://127.0.0.1:8080/manager/html/</uri>
<uri>http://127.0.0.1:8080/admin/</uri>
        </pre>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Future</title>
    <section>
      <title>Future possibilities for Tomcat on Gentoo</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          These are some things that are either in consideration, the works, or would be
          nice to have the abilities added to the Tomcat ebuild, or related to Tomcat on
          Gentoo Linux.
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>
        	    Gentoo Web Application integration support per
              <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0011.html">GLEP 11</uri>
              </li>
              <li>
        	    Replace init script with one developed by a Tomcat developer
   <uri>http://www.webdroid.org:8080/repo/viewcvs.cgi/tomcat-package/trunk/bin/</uri>
              </li>
              <li>
                Documentation on Tomcat's connectors and using them to connect to
                Apache on Gentoo Linux.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Problems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Where and who to report what to</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          If you have problems, please stop and think if the problem is Gentoo related, or
          Tomcat specific. If you are not sure, please start with the Gentoo Java
          community and team. Which can be reached via the gentoo-java mailing list, or
          #gentoo-java irc channel on freenode.net. Please file and report Gentoo related
          bugs, feature enhancement requests, and etc to
          <uri>http://bugs.gentoo.org/</uri>
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

</guide>
